Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.14
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dick Thornburgh Papers, Series XIV. Campaign for United States Senate
1991
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thornburgh, Dick
AIS.1998.30.14
60 Linear Feet
When Dick Thornburgh resigned as Attorney General of the United States in early August 1991 only three months remained before Election Day. His opponent, Harris Wofford, had been appointed interim senator by Pennsylvania Governor Casey after the tragic death of U.S. Senator John Heinz. Thornburgh's announcement speech touched upon his ability to effectively represent Pennsylvania's interests in Washington. The Wofford campaign focused almost exclusively on the issue of health-care reform. Even with a successful gubernatorial record to remind voters of, Thornburgh's messages were subsumed in larger national issues and Wofford handily won, his election seen as a wake-up call to Washington. The extent of voter discontent was seen in President Bush's subsequent defeat in the 1992 presidential election. The Thornburgh campaign files include extensive research on all issues, media ads (both transcripts and online videos), debate preparation and transcripts. The files are in the following sections: Speeches; News Releases; Campaign in Progress; Questionnaires; Schedules and Events; Candidate Thornburgh's Files; Ginny Thornburgh Files; Issue Research; Wofford Opposition Research; News Clippings; Ephemera; and Kirkpatrick & Lockhart (K&L) Files. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dick Thornburgh, February 27, 1998.
Previous Citation
Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932-, AIS.1998.30, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Personal papers; Government; Politics; Pennsylvania -- Economic conditions; Women; Political campaigns -- Pennsylvania; Thornburgh, Ginny (Judson); Thornburgh, Dick; United States. Congress. Senate -- Elections, 1980; Wofford, Harris; Kirkpatrick & Lockhart
- Campaign for U.S. Senate, 1991; XIV.
  Scope and Contents note
  Having resigned as Attorney General of the United States, and with less than three months before Election Day, planning for the campaign for U.S. Senate moved quickly. Staff was assembled, a media team was selected, and Evans Rose once again agreed to chair the fund-raising effort. That effort went well and President Bush appeared on Thornburgh's behalf at two events.
  The immediate goal was to touch political bases in Pennsylvania, knowing at the outset that there would be very little opportunity to put together a grassroots organization in such a short time. Running against a lesser known candidate in Harris Wofford, the two-month time frame was seen as a potential advantage. However, the campaign would need to depend heavily on the Republican organization to provide local level support and activity.
  Thornburgh's announcement speech touched upon all the themes to be emphasized during the campaign. One crucial paragraph, however, referring to "the corridors of power," was turned into a negative perception as supporting the status quo, rather than enabling Thornburgh to effectively represent Pennsylvania's interests in Washington as he had intended. This was but the beginning of a successful, and damaging media strategy by Wofford's chief campaign consultant, James Carville, who had "hammered Bill Scranton viciously in the 1986 gubernatorial campaign" (Evidence draft, p. 846).
  The central message of the Wofford campaign was stated in a Thornburgh-Wofford debate on September 6. "Early in [the] exchange, Senator Wofford displayed a pocket copy of the constitution and first raised the issue at which he would hammer for the rest of the campaign: 'If the constitution guarantees criminals the right to a lawyer, shouldn't it guarantee working Americans their right to a doctor as well?' Thereafter, most of his public message was focused almost exclusively on the issue of health-care reform, paying heed to the colorful words of James Carville: 'Reporters are like children in a school cafeteria. If you want them to eat spinach, don't put anything else on their plates' " (Evidence draft, p. 847). Although Thornburgh had spotted the health care issue as significant while still in Washington, even with good research and a serious proposal addressing the quality of care for all Americans, by the time it was presented it was effectively "too late and too little" (Evidence draft, p. 847).
  Although the Thornburgh campaign had a successful gubernatorial record to remind voters of, and Governor Casey's economic policies had eaten up the surplus and even the Rainy Day Fund left by Thornburgh, by the time of the election "voters were seen to vote against the candidate seen as most qualified and who would most effectively bring federal dollars to the state, namely Dick Thornburgh ... Post-mortem analysis characterized the election as a 'time for a change' election ... and by mid-October over 70% of the state's voters said the country was headed in the wrong direction. Thus, whatever message we sought to convey about this election was subsumed in larger national issues on the minds of the voters. Wofford was to characterize his effort from the outset as one designed to 'send a wake-up call to Washington'" (Evidence draft, p. 848).
  However, a valiant, committed Thornburgh campaign is well documented here. The schedules, the events, the extensive research on all issues thoughtfully and realistically presented, the constant campaign appearances by Thornburgh and his remarkable wife, Ginny, the speeches and news releases, the media ads, debate preparation and transcripts, and the successful fund-raising are all included. Also, there are the daily news clippings depicting the day to day progress of the campaign, as well as some campaign blunders, the increasingly evident lack of familiarity of campaign press staff with the state, and what appeared even to supporters and friends to be an inability of the campaign staff to even put the best foot forward. One Philadelphia Inquirer reporter, Kit Seelye, "credited Wofford with being 'guided by the more formidable campaign handlers, noting that I wasn't 'always well-served by my staff' ... and put the ultimate question as: 'Can an uncertain candidate [Wofford] with a sure-footed campaign overcome a sure-footed candidate [Thornburgh] with an uncertain campaign?' Her response? 'Stay tuned.'" (Evidence draft, p. 855).
  Ultimately, and ominously, the editorial endorsements, usually a source of strong Thornburgh support in previous campaigns, did an about-face. The Harrisburg Patriot, for example, concluded in its Sunday, October 27, editorial: "In the end, the decision really comes down to this: If you think the country is pretty much on the right course, Thornburgh is your man. If you think the nation has to address a number of serious domestic issues soon or face further economic and social deterioration, Wofford deserves your vote." All the major newspapers that had endorsed Thornburgh in his gubernatorial campaigns now went against him, and "the remaining steam did seem to go out of our effort" (Evidence draft, p. 859).
  Although by Election Day, November 5, the Thornburghs had felt the election slipping away, no one was prepared for the magnitude of the reversal, a 55% to 45% margin. In his election night remarks Thornburgh stated: "So I come before you this evening at a time of reversal, to be sure, but sustained by pride and fulfillment in having had the marvelous opportunities I have had over the past 25 years. I say reversal, and not defeat, because reversals are counted in the numbers; defeat can come only in the soul, and my soul's alive and kicking tonight!"
  "The effect of the election outcome was electrifying nationally ... Few put it as succinctly as Washington Post columnist Charles Krauthammer ('One way to view the Wofford victory is that if you campaign in depressed times and promise to pay everybody's doctor bills, you are likely to win.') ... The post election analysis prepared for [pollster] Bob Teeter found an astonishing 24% of those voting for Wofford 'feel that Thornburgh is more experienced and qualified to be U.S. Senator.' So much for the argument that one can swim effectively against the kind of tide that was developing in 1991 and which broke in full force during the 1992 presidential election ... Wofford, of course, was unable to fulfill his extravagant promises of free health care ... and was soundly defeated when he sought reelection" (Evidence draft, p. 862).
  The newspaper endorsements, campaign brochures, campaign ads (both transcripts and online videos), election results and election analyses are all included here. In addition, a final blow related to campaign debt, a case against Thornburgh resulting in his having to pay $350,000 with personal funds, is also documented here. This followed three years of litigation and surprisingly "established for the first time the legal obligation of a candidate, as distinguished from his or her campaign committee, for unpaid campaign bills" (Evidence, p. 314).
  The files are presented in the following sections: Speeches; News Releases; Campaign in Progress; Questionnaires; Schedules and Events; Candidate Thornburgh's Files; Ginny Thornburgh Files; Issue Research; Wofford Opposition Research; News Clippings, Ephemera; and Kirkpatrick & Lockhart (K & L) Files.
  - Speeches and Testimony, 1.
    The two principal speeches from the Campaign for U.S. Senate are both available here online. The files include additional drafts and notes. It will be of interest that the concession speech video is available here online.
    - Announcement Speech by Dick Thornburgh, Candidate for the United States Senate from the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, August 29 and 30, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 1)
    - Concession Speech, November 5, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 2)
  - News Releases, 2.
    All campaign news releases, September-November 6, 1991, have been digitized and are available here online. They follow the progress of the campaign are present a good overview.
    - September, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 3)
      - Republican State Committee of Pennsylvania states Senator Wofford in Violation of Federal Law, September 5, 1991; 1.
      - Thornburgh Commends Department of Justice for striking another blow at BCCI's international racketeering enterprises, September 5, 1991; 2.
      - Text of Thornburgh's New Campaign Ad "It's Simple", Undated; 3.
      - Statement regarding debate between Thornburgh and Wofford, September 6, 1991; 4.
      - Thornburgh Declares Victory in First Debate, September 6, 1991; 5.
      - Statement regarding Wofford's campaign commercials on Health Care and Fast-Track Authority, September 9, 1991; 6.
      - Statement regarding Wofford's news conference outside Department of Justice, September 11, 1991; 7.
      - White House News Release: Remarks by the President of the United States at Thornburgh for Senate Fundraiser, September 12, 1991; 8.
      - Thornburgh issues statement regarding the U.S. Department of Defense's announcement that an overhaul of aircraft carrier John F. Kennedy will occur at Philadelphia Naval Yard, September 17, 1991; 9.
      - Thornburgh tells Wofford to Explain Vote against Highway Money for Pennsylvania, September, 18, 1991; 10.
      - Text of Thornburgh's New Campaign Ad "Thank Goodness", September 18, 1991; 11.
      - Thornburgh Issues Statement on Philadelphia Naval Yard, September 19, 1991; 12.
      - Statement regarding Dick Thornburgh's Commitment to Senior Citizens, September 19, 1991; 13.
      - Thornburgh Calls for Increased Support for Small Business Exports, September 19, 1991; 14.
      - Vice President Quayle to Campaign for Thornburgh, September 20, 1991; 15.
      - Thornburgh supports $10 billion loan guarantee to Israel without any linkage to peace conference and would be co-sponsor of Kasten-Inouye legislation, September 23, 1991; 16.
      - Thornburgh Calls for "Industrial Renaissance" Initiative to Create Jobs at Abandoned Industrial Sites, September 23, 1991; 17.
      - Statement regarding new television commercial released by Wofford, September 25, 1991; 18.
      - Pennsylvania State Troopers Endorse Thornburgh for Senate, September 25, 1991; 19.
      - Text of Thornburgh's New Campaign Ad "Prove It", September 25, 1991; 20.
      - Dick Thornburgh Fighting for Lower Taxes, September 25, 1991; 21.
      - Thornburgh Calls for Phase-Out of Social Security Earnings Test, September 26, 1991; 22.
      - Thornburgh issued statement regarding death of Edward T. Hoak, State Adjutant of the American Legion in Pennsylvania, September 30, 1991; 23.
    - October-November, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 4)
      - Thornburgh's statement regarding his discussions with President on issue of extending unemployment compensation, October 2, 1991; 1.
      - Thornburgh's statement regarding Harris Wofford's Philadelphia news conference, October 3, 1991; 2.
      - Text of Thornburgh's New Campaign Ad "Fight", October 3, 1991; 3.
      - Dick Thornburgh Fighting for Jobs, October 3, 1991; 4.
      - Thornburgh Urges Congressional Support for School Reform Initiatives, October 4, 1991; 5.
      - Wofford Admits to Lack of Ideas for Pennsylvania, October 7, 1991; 6.
      - Statement regarding Harris Wofford's new television commercial, October 7, 1991; 7.
      - Thornburgh's letter to Wofford regarding plans for job creation in PA, October 9, 1991; 8.
      - Farmers for Thornburgh Group Launched, October 10, 1991; 9.
      - Thornburgh Calls for Federal Enterprise Zone Legislation, October 10, 1991; 10.
      - Gephardt Backs "Fast-Track" Authority, October 10, 1991; 11.
      - Three Pennsylvania Congressmen Demand Wofford Release Secret Health Care Plan, October 10, 1991; 12.
      - Thornburgh's Statement regarding President Bush's Veto of Legislation to Extend Unemployment Compensation, October 11, 1991; 13.
      - Text of Thornburgh's New Campaign Commercial "You Decide", October 11, 1991; 14.
      - Letter to Editor of Philadelphia Inquirer correcting inaccuracies in Katherine Seelye's account of criticism by partisan opponents of Thornburgh, "Ignoring his Stint at Justice", October 13, 1991; 15.
      - Thornburgh Urges Prompt Action on Multilateral Steel Agreement to Protect Steel Jobs against Unfair Foreign Competition, October 15, 1991; 16.
      - Thornburgh's Statement on his Record of Service to Senior Citizens (In Response to Times-Leader Article of October 15, 1991), 17.
      - Thornburgh Campaign Calls Wofford Ad a "Fairy Tale", October 15, 1991; 18.
      - Thornburgh's Statement regarding the Senate's Confirmation of Judge Clarence Thomas to the U.S. Supreme Court, October 15, 1991; 19.
      - Thornburgh's Response to Wofford's Latest Television Commercial, October 16, 1991; 20.
      - Thornburgh Calls for Overhaul of Senate Confirmation Process, October 16, 1991; 21.
      - Thornburgh Praises Barr Nomination, October 16, 1991; 22.
      - Thornburgh's Statement regarding Harris Wofford's Remarks on Floor of Senate about Health Care, October 17, 1991; 23.
      - Thornburgh Proposes New Federal Technology Issue to Create and Retain Jobs, October 21, 1991; 24.
      - Thornburgh Wins KQV Radio Poll, October 21, 1991; 25.
      - Thornburgh Calls on Wofford to Return Dirty Campaign Cash: "Wofford Has A Lot of Questions to Answer", October 22, 1991; 26.
      - Letter to Editor of U.S. News and World Report in response to October 7, 1991 Editorial, "Death on our Doorsteps", October 22, 1991; 27.
      - Death Penalty for Drug King Pins. Thornburgh: Supports. Wofford: Opposes, Undated; 28.
      - Thornburgh's Statement regarding Press Conference by Harris Wofford and Jack Blum, October 23, 1991; 29.
      - Text of Thornburgh's New Campaign Ad "First Right", October 23, 1991; 30.
      - Thornburgh Calls for Federal Enterprise Zone Legislation, October 23, 1991; 31.
      - Prominent Labor Groups Endorse Thornburgh for Senate, October 24, 1991; 32.
      - Wofford Donates Money to Charity to Justify TV Commercial, October 26, 1991; 33.
      - Thornburgh Issues Six-Point Plan for Congressional Reform, October 28, 1991; 34.
      - Thornburgh Calls for Tax Relief for Working Families, October 29, 1991; 35.
      - Thornburgh Announces 14-Point Plan for Affordable Health Care, October 30, 1991; 36.
      - Thornburgh Calls for New Federal Initiatives to Create and Preserve Jobs, October 31, 1991; 37.
      - Text of Thornburgh's New Campaign Commercial "Health Care", November 1, 1991; 38.
      - Thornburgh Calls for Expanded Federal Efforts to Attack Violent Crime and Drug Trafficking, November 2, 1991; 39.
      - Seniors Defend Thornburgh's Record, November 2, 1991; 40.
      - Thornburgh Says National Health Insurance Could Cost Pennsylvania Jobs, November 4, 1991; 41.
      - Thornburgh Campaign Denounces Disgruntled Former Staff Members, November 4, 1991; 42.
      - Thornburgh to Hold Post-Election News Conference Today, November 6, 1991; 43.
  - Campaign in Progress, 3.
    Among the scores of material generated during any campaign for political office, there are those core files that really can be called "the campaign" files, here referred to as "campaign in progress." These include such items as correspondence, media appearances and advertisements, financial information, and scheduling, etc. They are the foundation upon which a campaign proceeds up to and including election day, and essentially track its progress. A court case challenging the procedures for filling the Senate vacancy delayed the onset of Thornburgh's campaign. Within a week after the court decision on August 6th, Thornburgh submitted his resignation as Attorney General, and the campaign was off and running. Researchers will be interested in the online videos available here of campaign ads and Thornburgh's concession speech on election night, November 5, 1991.
    The "Campaign in Progress" files are organized in the ten following sections: 1) Campaign actions and issues, including staff files, general campaign files and endorsements; 2) Media, including transcripts of the debates between Thornburgh and Harris Wofford, press kits, mailings sent by campaign staff to editorial writers, and other coverage by newsletters and bulletins; 3) Campaign issue statements, released by the Thornburgh campaign, arranged chronologically by date; 4) Opposition research regarding Harris Wofford's record and campaign issues; 5) Campaign briefing binders, documenting Thornburgh's and Wofford's positions on issues, campaign strategies, and other research; 6) Finances, including receipts and expenditure reports, campaign contributions, and FEC fundraising reports; 7) Pennsylvania county briefing materials, including general information and history for each, arranged alphabetically by county name; 8) Campaign correspondence, including two separate groups of materials: general correspondence to and from Thornburgh (arranged alphabetically by sender's last name) and post-election condolence letters and responses (also arranged alphabetically by sender's last name); 9) Election results and post-election analyses, including post-election coverage and reports; 10) Articles and news clippings, including one section of clippings used for research on comparative positives and negatives of Dick Thornburgh, Harris Wofford, and Robert P. Casey (including his gubernatorial officials William Keisling and Donald Mazziotti).
    - Campaign Actions and Issues
      - Volunteer requests, June-September, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 5)
      - Telephone etiquette and volunteer phone banks, September-October, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 6)
      - Contacts for information on various issues, September, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 7)
      - Memorandum from Harold Miller regarding campaign strategy, July 29, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 8)
      - Scheduling, events and speaking requests, September, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 9)
      - Campaign staff contacts and biographies of Ginny and Dick Thornburgh, April-August, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 10)
      - "Dick Thornburgh: Rhetoric v. Reality," by Citizens for Senator Wofford in response to Thornburgh's announcement speech, September 2, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 11)
      - Responses to Democrat charges about Thornburgh tax increases, September 3, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 12)
      - Thornburgh campaign endorsements list, September-October, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 13)
      - Bedford County Press Endorsement, September 4, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 14)
      - Lancaster New Era Endorsement, September 14, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 15)
      - Pennsylvania State Troopers Association Endorsement, September 25, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 16)
      - National Association of Whole-saler Distributors Endorsement, October, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 17)
      - Pennsylvania State Troopers Association Endorsement, October 8, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 18)
      - Johnstown Tribune Democrat Endorsement, October 20, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 19)
      - Transport Workers Union of America Endorsement, October 22, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 20)
      - National Federation of Independent Business Endorsement, October 28, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 21)
      - Citizens for Law and Order (CLO) Endorsement, October 30, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 22)
      - Pennsylvania Pro-Life Federation PAC Endorsement, undated (Box 912, Folder 23)
      - Endorsement letter from President Ronald Reagan, undated (Box 912, Folder 24)
      - Pro-Thornburgh "Letters to the Editor campaign", October, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 25)
      - Murray Dickman's files, regarding voter turnout and campaign mailings, etc., June-October, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 26)
      - Paul Critchlow's files, regarding media and public relations, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 27)
      - Direct Opinions poll: "Thornburgh is the Top Choice for Pennsylvania Senator", July 25, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 28)
      - Miscellaneous campaign material, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 29)
    - Media
      - The Media Team (public relations consultants), strategies, issues and ads, July-August, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 30)
      - Media summary prepared by the Media Team, and notes, September 3-9, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 31)
      - CNN "Evans and Novak" regarding Thornburgh's career as Attorney General and upcoming candidacy for U.S. Senate, August 17-19, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 32)
      - Thornburgh and Wofford debate, "The Editors", September 6, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 33)
      - Thornburgh and Wofford debate, Pennsylvania Association of Broadcasters, October 18, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 34)
      - Memorandum to Thornburgh from Dan Eramian regarding election press appearances, November 2, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 35)
      - Thornburgh advertisements, August-November, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 36)
      - Wofford advertisements, August-November, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 37)
      - Commercial script drafts, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 38)
      - "A Look at Nate Smith," Black Opinion magazine, Thornburgh photo with Nate Smith, president of Operations Dig and Careers (a Pittsburgh-based career and development program), May-June, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 39)
      - Keystone Gazette article by Dick Thornburgh regarding his Senate campaign and his record as Governor, May-November, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 40)
      - Direct mailings, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 41)
      - Campaign press kit, 1991 (Box 912, Folder 42)
      - Campaign article mailing, October, 1991 (Box 913, Folder 1)
      - Announcement speech, news clippings and statements sent to editorial writers, September, 1991 (Box 913, Folder 2)
      - Factual analysis on Wofford advertisements, sent to editorial writers, October 1-16, 1991 (Box 913, Folder 3)
      - Clippings and news releases sent to editorial writers, October 11, 1991 (Box 913, Folder 4)